Chris Anderson: So I guess what we're going to do is
(كريس أندرسون): ما سنقوم بفعله
we're going to talk about your life,
أننا سوف نتحدث عن حياتك
and using some pictures that you shared with me.
مستخدمًا بعض الصور التي قمت بمشاركتها معي
And I think we should start right here with this one.
وأظن أننا ينبغي أن نبدأ الآن بهذه الصورة
Okay, now who is this?
حسنًا، من هذا؟
Martine Rothblatt: This is me with our oldest son Eli.
(مارتين روث بلات): هذه صورة لي مع ابني الأكبر (إيلاي)
He was about age five.
كان تقريبًا في الخامسة من عمره
This is taken in Nigeria
والتُقِطَت في (نيجيريا)
right after having taken the Washington, D.C. bar exam.
بعد إجراء اختبار ممارسة القانون في (واشنطن)
CA: Okay. But this doesn't really look like a Martine.
(كريس): ولكن هذا لا يشبهك تمامًا
MR: Right. That was myself as a male, the way I was brought up.
(مارتين): حقًا، ذلك أنها صورة لي عندما كنت ذكرًا كما تم تنشئتي
Before I transitioned from male to female and Martin to Martine.
قبل أن أتحول من ذكر لأنثى ومن (مارتن) لـ(مارتين)
CA: You were brought up Martin Rothblatt.
(كريس): تم تنشئتك كـ(مارتن روث بلات)؟
MR: Correct.
(مارتين): نعم
CA: And about a year after this picture, you married a beautiful woman.
(كريس): وبعد حوالي عام من التقاط هذه الصورة تزوجت امرأة جميلة
Was this love at first sight? What happened there?
هل كان هذا حبًا من أول نظرة؟ ما قصة زواجك؟
MR: It was love at the first sight.
(مارتن): لقد كان حبًا من أول نظرة
I saw Bina at a discotheque in Los Angeles,
فقد رأيت (بينا) في حانَةُ رَقْص في (لوس أنجيليس)
and we later began living together,
وبعد ذلك بقترة انتقلنا للعيش معًا
but the moment I saw her, I saw just an aura of energy around her.
ولكن عندما رأيتها رأيت هالة من الطاقة حولها
I asked her to dance.
طلبت منها أن نرقص سويًا
She said she saw an aura of energy around me.
فقالت لي أنها رأت هالة من الطاقة تحيط بي
I was a single male parent. She was a single female parent.
كنت حينها أب أعزب وكانت هي أم عزباء
We showed each other our kids' pictures,
وقام كل منا بعرض صور أطفاله على الآخر
and we've been happily married for a third of a century now.
ونحن ننعم بزواج سعيد لثلث قرن لوقتنا هذا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: And at the time, you were kind of this hotshot entrepreneur,
(كريس): في ذلك الحين كنت رجل أعمال بارع
working with satellites.
في مجال الأقمار الصناعية
I think you had two successful companies,
أظن أنك كان لديك شركتان ناجحتان
and then you started addressing this problem
وعندئذ شرعت في العمل على قضية
of how could you use satellites to revolutionize radio.
كيفية استخدام الأقمار الصناعية لإحداث ثورة في الإذاعة
Tell us about that.
حدثنا عن ذلك.
MR: Right. I always loved space technology,
(مارتن): لطالما كنت مولعًا بتكنولوجيا الفضاء
and satellites, to me, are sort of like the canoes that our ancestors
والأقمار الصناعية لي كالزوارق التي دفع بها أجدادنا
first pushed out into the water.
إلى الماء بداية للإبحار
So it was exciting for me to be part of the navigation
لذا شعرت بالمتعة كوني جزءًا من عملية الإبحار
of the oceans of the sky,
في محيطات السماء
and as I developed different types of satellite communication systems,
وأثناء قيامي بتطوير أنواع مختلفة من أنظمة اتصالات الأفمار الصناعية
the main thing I did was to launch bigger and more powerful satellites,
كان أهم ما فعلت هو إطلاق أقمار صناعية أكبر وأقوى
the consequence of which was that the receiving antennas
الأمر الذي أدى إلى إمكانية جعل هوائيات الاستقبال
could be smaller and smaller,
أصغر فأصغر
and after going through direct television broadcasting,
وبعد الخوض في البث التلفزيوني المباشر
I had the idea that if we could make a more powerful satellite,
راودتني فكرة أننا إذا استطعنا صنع قمر صناعي أكثر قوة
the receiving dish could be so small
يمكن أن يكون طبق الاستقبال صغيرًا للغاية
that it would just be a section of a parabolic dish,
ليكون مجرد جزء بسيط من هوائي مكافئ
a flat little plate embedded into the roof of an automobile,
صفيحة صغيرة مسطحة مزروعة في سقف السيارة
and it would be possible to have nationwide satellite radio,
وسيكون من الممكن صنع هوائي يغطي البلد بأكملها ويعمل عن طريق القمر الصناعي
and that's Sirius XM today.
وهو ما يحمل اسم (Sirius XM) في يومنا هذا.
CA: Wow. So who here has used Sirius?
(كريس): رائع، من هنا يستخدم (Sirius)؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
MR: Thank you for your monthly subscriptions.
(مارتين): شكرًا على اشتراكاتكم الشهرية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CA: So that succeeded despite all predictions at the time.
(كريس): لقد نجح هذا الأمر بالرغم من كل التكهنات حينذٍ
It was a huge commercial success,
لقد حقق نجاحًا تجاريًا كبيرًا
but soon after this, in the early 1990s,
ولكن بعد هذا النجاح بقليل وفي مطلع التسعينات
there was this big transition in your life and you became Martine.
حدث تحول كبير في حياتك وأصبحت (مارتين)
MR: Correct. CA: So tell me, how did that happen?
(مارتين): صحيح (كريس): أخبرني كيف حدث هذا التحول؟
MR: It happened in consultation with Bina and our four beautiful children,
(مارتين): حدث هذا بعد مشاورة (بينا) وأطفالنا الأربعة الرائعين.
and I discussed with each of them
تحدثت إلى كل منهم.
that I felt my soul was always female, and as a woman,
وأخبرتهم بأني لطالما شعرت بأن روحي أنثوية وأني امرأة
but I was afraid people would laugh at me if I expressed it,
ولكني كنت أخشى أن يسخر الناس مني إن عبرت عن ذلك
so I always kept it bottled up
ولذا، أضمرت هذا الأمر بداخلي
and just showed my male side.
وأظهرت جانبي الذكوري فقط
And each of them had a different take on this.
وكان لكل منهم موقف مختلف عن الآخر حيال ذلك
Bina said, "I love your soul,
فقد قالت (بينا): "أحب روحك
and whether the outside is Martin and Martine,
وسواء كان الشكل الخارجي (مارتن) أو (مارتين)
it doesn't it matter to me, I love your soul."
لا يهمني، فأنا أحب روحك"
My son said, "If you become a woman, will you still be my father?"
وقال ابني: "هل ستظل أبي إذا تحولت إلى امرأة؟"
And I said, "Yes, I'll always be your father,"
فقلت: "نعم، سأظل أباك للأبد"
and I'm still his father today.
ولا زلت أباه لليوم
My youngest daughter did an absolutely brilliant five-year-old thing.
أما ابنتي الصغرى ذات الخمس أعوام آنذاك، فقد فعلت أمرًا رائعًا حقًا
She told people, "I love my dad and she loves me."
حيث قالت للناس: "أحب أبي و هي تحبني"
So she had no problem with a gender blending whatsoever.
فلم يكن لديها أية مشكلة تذكر مع تغيير الجنس
CA: And a couple years after this, you published this book:
(كريس): وبعد سنتين من هذا الحدث، نشرت كتابك المعنون:
"The Apartheid of Sex."
"التمييز العنصري في الجنس"
What was your thesis in this book?
ماذا كان موضوعك في هذا الكتاب؟
MR: My thesis in this book is that there are seven billion people in the world,
(مارتن): موضوعي في هذا الكتاب أن هناك سبعة مليار شخص في هذا العالم
and actually, seven billion unique ways to express one's gender.
وهناك في الواقع سبعة مليارات طريقة مختلفة يمكن للمرء من خلالها التعبير عن جنسه
And while people may have the genitals of a male or a female,
وعلى الرغم من وجود أعضاء تناسلية ذكرية أو أنثوية لدى الناس
the genitals don't determine your gender
لا تحدد تلك الأعضاء جنس المرء
or even really your sexual identity.
ولا حتى هويته الجنسية
That's just a matter of anatomy
فهذا أمر يتعلق بالتشريح فحسب
and reproductive tracts,
وقنوات للتوالد،
and people could choose whatever gender they want
وبوسع الناس اختيار الجنس الذي يريدون
if they weren't forced by society into categories of either male or female
إذا لم يصنفهم المجتمع رغمًا عنهم إلى ذكور أو إناث
the way South Africa used to force people into categories of black or white.
كما اعتادت جنوب افريقيا على تصنيف الناس إلى سود وبيض
We know from anthropological science that race is fiction,
ونحن نعلم من علم الأنثروبولوجي أن العرق أمر خيالي
even though racism is very, very real,
حتى لو كانت العنصرية على اساس العرق حقيقة
and we now know from cultural studies
وكذلك نعلم من الدراسات الثقافية
that separate male or female genders is a constructed fiction.
أن الأجناس الذكرية الخالصة والأنثوية الخالصة هي خيال مصطنع.
The reality is a gender fluidity
وأن هناك في الواقع سيولة جنسية
that crosses the entire continuum from male to female.
التي تنتقل تماما من حيز الذكورة إلى الأنثوية
CA: You yourself don't always feel 100 percent female.
(كريس): أنت نفسك لا تشعر دومًا بأنك أنثى 100 بالمائة.
MR: Correct. I would say in some ways
(مالرتن): حقًا، يمكنني القول بأنني
I change my gender about as often as I change my hairstyle.
أغير جنسي كثيرًا وكأني أغير تصفيفة شعري
CA: (Laughs) Okay, now, this is your gorgeous daughter, Jenesis.
(كريس): حسنًا، هذه هي ابنتك الجميلة (جينسيس)
And I guess she was about this age when something pretty terrible happened.
وأظن أنها كانت في هذه المرحلة العمرية عندما حدث أمر مروع.
MR: Yes, she was finding herself unable to walk up the stairs
(مارتن): نعم، فقد وجدت أنها لا تستطيع صعود الدرج
in our house to her bedroom,
في منزلنا للذهاب لغرفتها
and after several months of doctors,
وبعد عدة شهور من الفحوصات
she was diagnosed to have a rare, almost invariably fatal disease
شخص الأطباء حالتها على أنها تعاني من مرض فتاك دائم
called pulmonary arterial hypertension.
يسمى فرط ضغط الدم في الشريان الرئوي
CA: So how did you respond to that?
(كريس): كيف تعاملت مع هذا الأمر؟
MR: Well, we first tried to get her to the best doctors we could.
(مارتن): حسنًا، حاولنا في البداية عرضها على أفضل الأطباء
We ended up at Children's National Medical Center in Washington, D.C.
وانتهى بنا الحال في (المركز الطبي القومي للأطفال) في (واشنطن)
The head of pediatric cardiology
وأخبرنا رئيس قسم قلب الأطفال
told us that he was going to refer her to get a lung transplant,
بأنه سوف يقوم بنقلها لتُجرى لها عملية نقل رئة
but not to hold out any hope,
لكنه أخبرني ألا نعقد آمالاً عليها
because there are very few lungs available,
لعدم وجود عدد كبير من الرئات المتوفرة
especially for children.
خصوصًا للأطفال
He said that all people with this illness died,
قال أن كل الذين أصيبوا بهذا المرض ماتوا
and if any of you have seen the film "Lorenzo's Oil,"
وفي حال شاهد أي منكم فيلم "Lorenzo's Oil"
there's a scene when the protagonist
كان هناك مشهد يصور البطل
kind of rolls down the stairway crying and bemoaning the fate of his son,
وهو ينزل الدرج باكيًا ويندب مصير ابنه
and that's exactly how we felt about Jenesis.
وكان هذا ما شعرنا به تجاه (جنسيس)
CA: But you didn't accept that as the limit of what you could do.
(كريس): ولكن يبدوأنك لم تقبل أن يكون هذا أقصى ما تفعله
You started trying to research and see if you could find a cure somehow.
حيث بدأت في البحث لترى إذا كان بوسعك ايجاد علاج في مكان ما
MR: Correct. She was in the intensive care ward for weeks at a time,
(مارتن): حقًا، فقد أمضت أسابيع ذات مرة في وحدة العناية الفائقة
and Bina and I would tag team to stay at the hospital
وشكلت أنا و(بينا) فريقين على أن يقوم أحدهما بالبقاء في المستشفى
while the other watched the rest of the kids,
بينما يقوم الآخر برعاية بقية الأطفال
and when I was in the hospital and she was sleeping,
أثناء وجودي في المستشفى،عندما تكون (جينيسيس) نائمة،
I went to the hospital library.
كنت أذهب إلى مكتبة المستشفى.
I read every article that I could find on pulmonary hypertension.
قرأت هناك كل المقالات التي وجدتها عن فرط ضغط الدم الرئوي
I had not taken any biology, even in college,
لم ادرس البيولوجيا في الجامعة
so I had to go from a biology textbook to a college-level textbook
لذا، كنت أتنقل بين كتب البيولوجيا الى الكتب الجامعية عن البيولوجيا
and then medical textbook and the journal articles, back and forth,
ثم الى الكتب الطبية والمقالات الأكاديمية
and eventually I knew enough to think that it might be possible
وتدريجيًا، تولدت لدي معرفة كافية للإعتقاد بإمكانية
that somebody could find a cure.
ايجاد علاج.
So we started a nonprofit foundation.
لذا، شرعنا في إنشاء منظمة غير ربحية.
I wrote a description asking people to submit grants
وفي تعريفي لنشاط المنظمة طلبت من الناس التبرع لها
and we would pay for medical research.
على أن نقوم نحن بتحمل تكاليف البحث الطبي.
I became an expert on the condition -- doctors said to me, Martine,
أصبحت خبيرًا في هذه الحالة وقال لي الأطباء: "مارتين،
we really appreciate all the funding you've provided us,
نحن نقدر التمويل الذي قدمته لنا
but we are not going to be able to find a cure in time
ولكننا لن نكون قادرين على ايجاد علاج في الوقت المناسب
to save your daughter.
لإنقاذ حياة ابنتك.
However, there is a medicine
وعلى أية حال، هناك دواء
that was developed at the Burroughs Wellcome Company
"تم تطويره في شركة (Burroughs wellcome)
that could halt the progression of the disease,
يمكن من خلاله إيقاف تطور المرض
but Burroughs Wellcome has just been acquired by Glaxo Wellcome.
ولكن شركة (Burroughs Wellcome) تم شراؤها من قبل(Glaxo Wellcome).
They made a decision not to develop
وقد اتخذوا قرارًا بإيقاف تطوير
any medicines for rare and orphan diseases,
أية ادوية تعالج امراضاََ انادرة و مهملة،
and maybe you could use your expertise in satellite communications
وربما يكون بوسعك استغلال خبرتك في مجال اتصالات الأقمار الصناعية
to develop this cure for pulmonary hypertension.
في تطوير علاج لفرط ضغط الدم الرئوي."
CA: So how on earth did you get access to this drug?
(كريس): كيف تمكنت من الوصول إلى هذا العقار؟
MR: I went to Glaxo Wellcome
(مارتن): ذهبت إلى (Glaxo Wellcome )
and after three times being rejected and having the door slammed in my face
فأغلقوا الباب في وجهي ورفضوا مقابلتي لثلاث مرات
because they weren't going to out-license the drug
لأنهم لم يكونوا على استعداد لترخيص الدواء
to a satellite communications expert,
لخبير في مجال تكنولوجيا اتصالات الأقمار الصناعية
they weren't going to send the drug out to anybody at all,
ولم يكن لديهم استعداد لإعطاء الدواء لأي أحد في الخارج مهما كان
and they thought I didn't have the expertise,
وظنوا أني لا أمتلك الخبرة
finally I was able to persuade a small team of people to work with me
ولكني تمكنت في نهاية المطاف من إقناع فريق صغير من الناس بالعمل معي
and develop enough credibility.
لايجاد مصداقية كافية.
I wore down their resistance,
ارهقتهم،
and they had no hope this drug would even work, by the way,
ولم يكن لديهم أمل في نجاح هذا الدواء،
and they tried to tell me, "You're just wasting your time.
وحاولوا أن يقولوا لي: "أنت تضيع وقتك فحسب
We're sorry about your daughter."
نحن حقًا نشعر بالأسف حيال ابنتك."
But finally, for 25,000 dollars
ولكن في النهاية وفي مقابل 25,000$
and agreement to pay 10 percent of any revenues we might ever get,
واتفاق يحصلوا بموجبه على 10% من أية عوائد قد نحصل عليها
they agreed to give me worldwide rights to this drug.
وافقوا على إعطائي حقوق هذا الدواء في كل دول العالم.
CA: And so you put this drug on the market in a really brilliant way,
(كريس): قمت بطرح الدواء في السوق بطريقة رائعة حقًا
by basically charging what it would take to make the economics work.
حيث قمت بتسعيره وفقكما تقتضي الحاجة لضمان نجاحه اقتصادياََ.
MR: Oh yes, Chris, but this really wasn't a drug that I ended up --
(مارتين): حقًا (كريس)، ولكن لم يكن هذا عقارًا وصلت إليه
after I wrote the check for 25,000,
بعد أن دفعت شيكًا بقيمة 25,000
and I said, "Okay, where's the medicine for Jenesis?"
فقد قلت: "حسنًا، أين علاج (جينيسيس)؟"
they said, "Oh, Martine, there's no medicine for Jenesis.
قالوا لي: "(مارتين)، ليس هناك دواء لـ(جينيسيس)،
This is just something we tried in rats."
فهذا دواء جربناه على الفئران فحسب."
And they gave me, like, a little plastic Ziploc bag
أعطوني حقيبة صغيرة من البلاستيك تغلق بسحابة
of a small amount of powder.
وبداخلها قليل من مسحوق.
They said, "Don't give it to any human,"
وقالوا لي: "لا تعطيها لأي انسان"
and they gave me a piece of paper which said it was a patent,
وأعطوني قصاصة ورقية تقول بأن هذا المسحوق مسجل ببراءة اختراع
and from that, we had to figure out a way to make this medicine.
وكان لزامًا علينا أن نجد طريقة نصنع بها الدواء من هذا المسحوق.
A hundred chemists in the U.S. at the top universities
أقسم مائة من الكيميائيين في كبرى الجامعات في الولايات المتحدة
all swore that little patent could never be turned into a medicine.
على استحالة تحويل هذا الاختراع الصغير إلى دواء
If it was turned into a medicine, it could never be delivered
وإذا تم تحويل المسحوق إلى دواء يستحيل توصيله للجسم بفاعلية
because it had a half-life of only 45 minutes.
لأن عُمُرِه النِّصْفي يقدر 45 دقيقة فحسب.
CA: And yet, a year or two later, you were there with a medicine
(كريس): ومع ذلك، توصلت، بعد سنة أو سنتين، إلى دواء
that worked for Jenesis.
عالج (جينيسيس).
MR: Chris, the astonishing thing is that this absolutely worthless
(مارتن): الشيء المذهل (كريس) أن هذا
piece of powder
المسحوق عديم القيمة
that had the sparkle of a promise of hope for Jenesis
الذي منح (جينيسيس) بصيصًا من الأمل
is not only keeping Jenesis and other people alive today,
لا يحافظ على حياتها وغيرها من الناس في يومنا هذا فحسب
but produces almost a billion and a half dollars a year in revenue.
بل أيضًا يدر ما يقرب من مليار ونصف المليار دولار من العوائد سنويًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: So here you go.
(كريس): تلك هي القصة إذن.
So you took this company public, right?
قمت بالإعلان عن شركتك، أليس كذلك؟
And made an absolute fortune.
وحققت ثروة محققة.
And how much have you paid Glaxo, by the way, after that 25,000?
بالمناسبة، كم دفعت لشركة (Glaxo) بعد هذا المبلغ المقدر بـ 25,000؟
MR: Yeah, well, every year we pay them 10 percent of 1.5 billion,
(مارتين): ندفع لهم 10% كل عام وقدرت حصتهم في المليار ونصف
150 million dollars, last year 100 million dollars.
بمائة وخمسين مليون دولار، وقد دفعنا لهم 100 مليون دولار العام الماضي
It's the best return on investment they ever received. (Laughter)
ويعد هذا أفضل عائد حصلوا عليه من جميع استثماراتهم (ضحك).
CA: And the best news of all, I guess,
(كريس): وأفضل ما في الأمر برمته
is this.
ما نراه.
MR: Yes. Jenesis is an absolutely brilliant young lady.
(مارتين): حقًا، فها هي (جنيسيس) أصبحت شابة متفوقة
She's alive, healthy today at 30.
ومفعمة بالحياة وتتمتع بالصحة وهي في الثلاثين من عمرها.
You see me, Bina and Jenesis there.
وها أنذا برفقة (بينا) و(جنيسيس).
The most amazing thing about Jenesis
الأمر المذهل حقًا أن (جنيسيس)
is that while she could do anything with her life,
وبالرغم من قدرتها على أن تحيا حياتها كيفما أرادت
and believe me, if you grew up your whole life with people
وصدقني، لو عشتَ حياتك مع أناس
in your face saying that you've got a fatal disease,
لا ينفكون عن تذكيرك بأن لديك مرض فتاك
I would probably run to Tahiti and just not want to run into anybody again.
ستفر إلى (تاهيتي) ولن تشعر بالرغبة في رؤية أحد ثانية.
But instead she chooses to work in United Therapeutics.
ولكن برغم ذلك، اختارت العمل في (United Therapeutics)
She says she wants to do all she can to help other people
تقول بأنها ترغب في فعل ما بوسعها لمساعدة الناس الذين يعانون من
with orphan diseases get medicines,
أمراض مهملة في الحصول على الدواء
and today, she's our project leader for all telepresence activities,
وتعمل حاليًا كقائدة لمشروعنا عن كل الاعمال التي تتطلب التواجد عن بعد،
where she helps digitally unite the entire company to work together
حيث تساعد في توحيد الشركة برمتها رقميًا للعمل سويًا
to find cures for pulmonary hypertension.
لايجاد علاج لفرط ضغط الدم الرئوي.
CA: But not everyone who has this disease has been so fortunate.
(كريس): برغم ذلك، لم يكن الحظ حليفًا لكل من عانى من هذا المرض
There are still many people dying, and you are tackling that too. How?
فهناك الكثير من الناس الذين يموتون وهذا موضوع بحثك أيضاً، كيف؟
MR: Exactly, Chris. There's some 3,000 people a year in the United States alone,
(مارتن): بالضبط (كريس)، فهناك ما يقرب من 3,000 شخص يموتون في الولايات المتحدة وحدها
perhaps 10 times that number worldwide,
في حين يموت عشرة أضعاف هذا الرقم في دول العالم أجمع
who continue to die of this illness
بسبب هذا المرض
because the medicines slow down the progression
ذلك أن الدواء بحد من تطور المرض
but they don't halt it.
ولكن لا يوقفه.
The only cure for pulmonary hypertension, pulmonary fibrosis,
العلاج الوحيد لفرط الدم الرئوي والتليف الرئوي
cystic fibrosis, emphysema,
والتليف الكيسي والنُفاخ الرئوي
COPD, what Leonard Nimoy just died of,
الداء الرئَويّ المسدّ المزمن، الذي مات بسببه (Leonard Nimoy)،
is a lung transplant,
هو زرع رئة،
but sadly, there are only enough available lungs for 2,000 people
ولكن العدد المتاح من الرئات لا يكفي للأسف لما يزيد عن 2,000 شخص
in the U.S. a year to get a lung transplant,
في الولايات المتحدة سنويًا كي يجرى لهم عملية زرع رئة
whereas nearly a half million people a year
بينما يموت سنويًا ما يقرب من نصف مليون شخص
die of end-stage lung failure.
بسبب فشل رئوي في المرحلة النهائية.
CA: So how can you address that?
(كريس): كيف يمكنك التعامل مع هذا؟
MR: So I conceptualize the possibility
(مارتن): مثلما يمكن لنا
that just like we keep cars and planes
الحفاظ على ديمومة حركة السيارات والطائرات
and buildings going forever
وإنشاء البنايات
with an unlimited supply of building parts and machine parts,
بتزويدها بقدر غير محدود من مواد بناء وأجزاء الآلات
why can't we create an unlimited supply of transplantable organs
أتصور أنه بإمكاننا توفير قدر غير محدود من الأعضاء القابلة للزرع
to keep people living indefinitely,
لإبقاء الناس على قيد الحياة دون توقف
and especially people with lung disease.
وخصوصُا هؤلاء الذين يعانون من مرض رئوي.
So we've teamed up with the decoder of the human genome, Craig Venter,
ولذلك كوّننا فريقا مع(Craig Venter) -الذي فك شيفرة الجينوم البشري -
and the company he founded
و الشركة التي اسسها
with Peter Diamandis, the founder of the X Prize,
مع (Peter Diamandis) -مؤسس جائزة اكس-
to genetically modify
للتعديل جينياََ
the pig genome
على جينوم الخنزير
so that the pig's organs will not be rejected by the human body
لكي لا يرفض جسم الانسان ما ينقل له من اعضاء الخنزير
and thereby to create an unlimited supply
وبالتالي ايجاد مصدر غير محدود
of transplantable organs.
للاعضاء التي يمكن زراعتها .
We do this through our company, United Therapeutics.
و نحن نقوم بهذا من خلال شركتنا "United Therapeutics"
CA: So you really believe that within, what, a decade,
(كريس): ايعني هذا انك تامل خلال العشر سنوات القادمة
that this shortage of transplantable lungs maybe be cured, through these guys?
انه يمكن حل مشكلة زراعة الرئة من خلال هؤلاء الخنازير؟
MR: Absolutely, Chris.
(مارتين): بالتأكيد،كريس.
I'm as certain of that as I was of the success that we've had
انا واثق من هذا كثقتي بالنجاح الذي نلناه
with direct television broadcasting, Sirius XM.
مع البث التلفازي المباشر -sirius xm-
It's actually not rocket science.
وهذا ليس صعبا كما تتخيلون.
It's straightforward engineering away one gene after another.
هي هندسة واضحة ، جين بعد جين
We're so lucky to be born in the time that sequencing genomes
نحن محظوظون كوننا ولدنا في الزمن الذي يعد تسلسل الجينوم البشري فيه
is a routine activity,
عملية روتينية ،
and the brilliant folks at Synthetic Genomics
و العاملين الاذكياء في شركة ( Synthetic Genomics)
are able to zero in on the pig genome,
قادرين على التحديد بدقة في جينوم الخنازير
find exactly the genes that are problematic, and fix them.
و ايجاد الجينات الممرضة خاصةََ و اصلاحها.
CA: But it's not just bodies that -- though that is amazing.
(كريس) :ولكن ليست فقد الاجساد .. مع ذلك ،هذا فعلا رائع.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's not just long-lasting bodies that are of interest to you now.
ولكن ليست الاجساد طويلة الامد وحدها ما يشغلك الان بل
It's long-lasting minds.
ايضا العقول طويلة الامد.
And I think this graph for you says something quite profound.
واظن ان هذا المخطط لك يقول شيئا عميقا .
What does this mean?
ما الذي يعنيه ؟
MR: What this graph means, and it comes from Ray Kurzweil,
(مارتين): ما يعنيه هذا المخطط -من مصممه ray kurzweil-
is that the rate of development in computer processing
ان سرعة التطور في المعالجة الحاسوبية
hardware, firmware and software,
في معدات الحاسوب و في برامج الحاسوب الثابتة و البرمجيات،
has been advancing along a curve
تتزايد مع المنحنى
such that by the 2020s, as we saw in earlier presentations today,
ما سيحدث انه في عام 2020 -كما راينا في عرض مسبق اليوم-
there will be information technology
سيكون هناك تكنولوجيا معلوماتية
that processes information and the world around us
تعالج المعلومات و العالم من حولنا
at the same rate as a human mind.
بسرعة مماثلة لسرعة العقل البشري.
CA: And so that being so, you're actually getting ready for this world
(كريس): و هذا يعني انك تستعد لهذا العالم
by believing that we will soon be able to, what,
بايمانك اننا قريبا سنكون قادرين على ماذا
actually take the contents of our brains and somehow preserve them forever?
على ان نأخذ محتويات عقولنا و نحفظهم بطريقة ما الى الابد؟
How do you describe that?
كيف تصف هذا ؟
MR: Well, Chris, what we're working on is creating a situation
(مارتين): حسنا،كريس، ما نعمل عليه هو خلق حالة
where people can create a mind file,
حيث يكون الناس قادرين على ايجاد ملف ذهني
and a mind file is the collection of their mannerisms, personality,
-والملف الذهني هو مجموعة من الخصوصيات، الشخصية،
recollection, feelings,
الذاكرة ،المشاعر،
beliefs, attitudes and values,
الاعتقادات،الاساليب والقيم ،
everything that we've poured today into Google, into Amazon, into Facebook,
كل شيء قمنا بوضعه في جوجل ،في امازون، في فيسبوك،
and all of this information stored there will be able, in the next couple decades,
وكل هذه المعلومات المخزنة هناك ستكون قادرة -خلال العقدين القادمين-
once software is able to recapitulate consciousness,
-عندما تصبح البرمجيات قادرة على تجميع الوعي -
be able to revive the consciousness which is imminent in our mind file.
على احياء الوعي المخيم في ملفات اذهاننا .
CA: Now you're not just messing around with this.
(كريس): حسنا، انت لست تعبث بهذا .
You're serious. I mean, who is this?
انت جاد فعلا . انا اعني، من هذا ؟
MR: This is a robot version of my beloved spouse, Bina.
(مارتين): هذا نسخة روبوتية من زوجتي الحبيبة بينا .
And we call her Bina 48.
نسميها بينا 48.
She was programmed by Hanson Robotics out of Texas.
تم برمجتها من قبل شركة ( Hanson Robotics ) في تكساس.
There's the centerfold from National Geographic magazine
هذه الصفحة الوسطى من مجلة ناشونال جيوجرافيك
with one of her caregivers,
مع احد مقدمي الرعاية الخاصة بها،
and she roams the web
وهي تتجول في الانترنت
and has hundreds of hours of Bina's mannerisms, personalities.
معها مئات الساعات من خصوصيات بينا و شخصياتها.
She's kind of like a two-year-old kid,
عمرها تقريبا سنتان
but she says things that blow people away,
لكنها تقول اشياء تصدم الناس
best expressed by perhaps
من الممكن ان اكثر ما يعبر عن هذا هو
a New York Times Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist Amy Harmon
قول الصحفية Amy Harmon -الحاصلة على جائزة Pulitzer- في صحيفة نيويورك تايمز
who says her answers are often frustrating,
تقول ان اجوبتها احيانا مخيبة للآمال
but other times as compelling as those of any flesh person she's interviewed.
واوقات اخرى تكون اجوبتها آسرة كاؤلائك الذين تجري معهم المقابلات.
CA: And is your thinking here, part of your hope here, is that
(كريس):وهل ما تعتقده هنا -او ما تأمله هنا-
this version of Bina can in a sense live on forever, or some future upgrade
ان هذه النسخة من بينا ستعيش للابد او ان تحديثاََ مستقبليا منها
to this version can live on forever?
سيعيش للابد ؟
MR: Yes. Not just Bina, but everybody.
(مارتين): اجل،ليست بينا وحدها لكن الجميع.
You know, it costs us virtually nothing to store our mind files
فعليا اعن ملية تخزين ملفاتنا الذهنية لا يكلفنا شيئاََ
on Facebook, Instagram, what-have-you.
على الفيسبوك و الانستجرام و مهما تملك منها.
Social media is I think one of the most extraordinary inventions of our time,
انا اعتقد ان وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي هي واحدة من اكثرالاختراعات اذهالا في زمننا،
and as apps become available that will allow us
وكما ان التطبيقات المتاحة التي تمكننا
to out-Siri Siri, better and better,
من تجاوز تطبيق Siri بشكل افضل بافضل ،
and develop consciousness operating systems,
و تطوير انظمة تشغيل الوعي
everybody in the world, billions of people,
كل الناس في العالم، المليارات من الاشخاص
will be able to develop mind clones of themselves
ستكون لهم القدرة على ايجاد نسخ ذهنية من انفسهم
that will have their own life on the web.
التي سيكون لها حياة خاصة بها في الانترنت.
CA: So the thing is, Martine,
(كريس): الوضع الان مارتين ،
that in any normal conversation, this would sound stark-staring mad,
اننا لو كنا في محادثة عادية ان هذا الحديث قد يبدو مجنوناََ جداََ
but in the context of your life, what you've done,
لكن في سياق حياتك ، ما فعلته فيها
some of the things we've heard this week,
بعضٌ مما سمعنا هذا الاسبوع
the constructed realities that our minds give,
الوقائع المشيدة التي تعطيها اذهاننا
I mean, you wouldn't bet against it.
هنا لا يمكنك ان تراهن ضده و تقول انه جنون .
MR: Well, I think it's really nothing coming from me.
(مارتين): صراحة انا لا اظن ان هذا بادر مني.
If anything, I'm perhaps a bit of a communicator of activities
ما اسهمت به هو ربما انني كنت نقطة وصل بين اعمال
that are being undertaken by the greatest companies
تقوم بها افضل الشركات
in China, Japan, India, the U.S., Europe.
في الصين و اليابان و الهند و امريكا و اوروبا.
There are tens of millions of people working on writing code
هناك عشرات الملايين من الناس التي تعمل على كتابة شيفرة
that expresses more and more aspects of our human consciousness,
تعبر عن جوانب كثيرة من وعينا البشري
and you don't have to be a genius to see that all these threads
ولا يستلزم الامر عبقريا ليرى ان هذه الخيوط
are going to come together and ultimately create human consciousness,
ستجتمع و تكون ككل الوعي البشري،
and it's something we'll value.
و هذا امرٌ سنقدره جدا.
There are so many things to do in this life,
هناك العديد من الاشياء التي يمكن فعلها بهذه الحياة
and if we could have a simulacrum, a digital doppelgänger of ourselves
ولو امكننا الحصول على شبيه رقمي زائف من انفسنا
that helps us process books, do shopping,
يمكنه مساعدتنا على معالجة الكتب و التبضع ،
be our best friends,
وان يكون صديقنا المفضل،
I believe our mind clones, these digital versions of ourselves,
أنا مؤمن بأن نسخنا الذهنية -هذه النسخ الرقمية من انفسنا-
will ultimately be our best friends,
ستكون صديقنا المفضل بالتأكيد
and for me personally and Bina personally,
وبالنسبة لي و لبينا شخصيا،
we love each other like crazy.
نحن نحب بعضنا بجنون .
Each day, we are always saying, like,
في كل يوم نقول لبعضنا اشياء مثل
"Wow, I love you even more than 30 years ago.
" واو، احبك اكثر من الثلاثين عام الماضيين"
And so for us, the prospect of mind clones
و هذا لنا -وجود النسخ الذهنية
and regenerated bodies
و الاجسام المتجددة-
is that our love affair, Chris, can go on forever.
ان قصة حبنا يا (كريس) ستستمر للابد.
And we never get bored of each other. I'm sure we never will.
و نحن لا نمل من بعضنا و انا متأكد اننا مستقبلا لن نمل ابدا.
CA: I think Bina's here, right? MR: She is, yeah.
(كريس): بينا هنا الان ،صحيح؟ (مارتين): اجل،هي هنا.
CA: Would it be too much, I don't know, do we have a handheld mic?
(كريس): هل سيكون صعبا ، لا اعلم ان امكننا ، هل يوجد مايك محمول ؟
Bina, could we invite you to the stage? I just have to ask you one question.
يبنا ، هل يمكن أن تشاركينا هنا على المسرح؟ أريد أن أسألك سؤالاََ واحداََ .
Besides, we need to see you.
غير اننا نريد رؤيتك .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you, thank you.
شكرا شكرا
Come and join Martine here.
تعالي وانضمي الى مارتين
I mean, look, when you got married,
عندما تزوجتما
if someone had told you that, in a few years time,
لو قال لك شخصٌ انه خلال سنوات قليلة قادمة
the man you were marrying would become a woman,
ان الرجل الذي تتزوجينه الان سيصبح امراة ،
and a few years after that, you would become a robot --
وبسنوات قليلة بعدها ستصبحين روبوتاّّ...
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
how has this gone? How has it been?
كيف كان كل هذا ؟
Bina Rothblatt: It's been really an exciting journey,
(بينا روذبلت): انها رحلة مشوقة جدا،
and I would have never thought that at the time,
ولم اكن لأظن هذا في ذلك الوقت ،
but we started making goals and setting those goals
لكننا بدأنا بعمل و وضع الاهداف
and accomplishing things,
وانجزنا اشياءََ ،
and before you knew it, we just keep going up and up
ومن دون وعيّ ، كنا نصعد لاعلى و اعلى
and we're still not stopping, so it's great.
و نحن لا نتوقف ولذلك هذا فعلا عظيم.
CA: Martine told me something really beautiful,
(كريس):مارتين قالت لي شيئا جميلا جدا ،
just actually on Skype before this,
على سكايب قبل هذا ،
which was that he wanted to live for hundreds of years
قال لي انه يريد ان يعيش لمئات السنين
as a mind file,
كملف ذهني
but not if it wasn't with you.
لكن ليس من دونك .
BR: That's right, we want to do it together.
(بينا): نعم صحيح، نحن نريد القيام بهذا معاََ.
We're cryonicists as well, and we want to wake up together.
و نحن نؤمن بالتجميد ايضا (cryopreservation) و نريد ان نستيقظ معا.
CA: So just so as you know, from my point of view,
(كريس): كما ترون و من منظوري الخاص
this isn't only one of the most astonishing lives I have heard,
هذه ليست فقط واحدة من اكثر الحيوات التي سمعت بها اذهالاََ
it's one of the most astonishing love stories I've ever heard.
بل اكثر قصص الحب التي سمعت به اذهالاََ.
It's just a delight to have you both here at TED.
كان من دواعي سرورنا استضافتكم هنا كليكما في TED.
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلاََ.
MR: Thank you.
(مارتين):شكرا لك.
(Applause)
تصفيق